Guide to the Charleston Cotton Exchange records, 1880-1952
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Charleston Cotton Exchange records 1880-1952
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Charleston Cotton Exchange (Charleston, S.C.)
3.0 Linear Feet 729 Items
The Charleston Cotton Exchange was founded in 1872 in the port of Charleston, South Carolina; one of its main functions was to provide commodity trading statistics to the mercantile community.
Collection includes minutes of the meetings of the Board of Directors in 1884; financial statements, 1896-1898, 1929-1930; letters of invitation to prospective members, 1910; and groups of reports on the cotton market at Charleston, 1936-1944, 1948-1950. The volumes contain detailed statistics on the shipping of cotton and other goods at Charleston, 1880-1905; cotton receipts at ports in the United States, 1899-1906; price quotations from several markets in naval stores, 1881-1886; and the finances of the Exchange, 1888-1938.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Charleston Cotton Exchange records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1971.
Collection Overview
These papers came to the library with those of the Cheshire, Sullivan and Canaday, cotton merchants of Charleston. Theophilus P. Cheshire and Solomon M. Canaday were presidents of the Exchange at various times during the 1930s to 1950s. The folder of cancelled checks, 1939-1952, contains checks bearing names of presidents during this period.
The chronological file of papers includes minutes of meetings of the Board of Directors in 1884, financial statements of 1896-1898 and 1929-1930, and a letter of invitation in 1910 to prospective members. A letter from President Cheshire in 1932 is a report on the finances of the exchange and the state of the cotton trade at Charleston. During 1948-1950, there are numerous reports of daily sales and inventories of cotton and frequent price quotations. A number of monthly reports record statistics on receipts and shipments of cotton.
Statistics on domestic and international shipments, inventories, and other data are in the Exchange's Report on Cotton Movement at Charleston, 1936-1944 that are filed in separate folders. The function of the Charleston Cotton Exchange as a provider of trading statistics to the mercantile community is represented by seven volumes. Marine News Clearances No. 2 (1880, July-1886, Aug.), and No. 5 (1899, Sept.-1905 Feb.) record shipping information: date of clearance, nationality, rig, name of vessel, master, destination, cargo (types of goods and their quantity), by whom cleared, and date of departure. Clearances No. 2, includes a List of Steamships Loaded at Charleston for Foreign Ports (1879, Sept.-1885, Sept.) that records the number of bales of Sea Island and upland cotton shipped, its destination, and other information. Marine Arrivals No. 3 (1886, Aug.-1892, Aug.), No. 4 (1892, Sept.-1899, Aug.), and No. 5 (1899, Sept.-1905, Feb.) list date of arrival, nationality, rig, name of vessel, master, place from which the ship had come, cargo (quantities not given), and consignee.
The Weekly Cotton Receipts at All U.S. Ports (1899, March-Sept., 1906) includes statistics for Galveston, New Orleans, Mobile, Savannah, Charleston, Wilmington, Norfolk, Baltimore, New York, Boston, Philadelphia, and other ports. These statistics include cumulative totals and comparative figures for the preceding year. Naval Stores No. 2 (1881, Sept.-July, 1886) contains price quotations (several times daily) for rosin and turpentine on the markets at Wilmington, New York, London, and Liverpool. Figures are more numerous for Wilmington and New York. In 1883 price quotations were begun for the market at Savannah, and those for Liverpool were discontinued. On the inside front cover is the Annual Statement of Stocks, Receipts and Exports for the Year Ended March 31st, 1882, Wilmington, N.C. (cotton, turpentine, rosin, tar, and crude). Four volumes record finances of the Exchange: Cashbook, June 1888-Dec, 1898; Cashbook, Jan., 1916-Aug., 1931; Cashbook, Sept., 1931-Aug., 1938; and the Assessments of Members, 1891-1916.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Cotton trade -- South Carolina -- Charleston
Cotton trade -- United States
Naval stores
Charleston (S.C.) -- Commerce
Charleston (S.C.) -- History
South Carolina -- Commerce
Related Material
Charleston Cotton Exchange records, 1872-1969
South Carolina Historical Society
Contents of Collection
- Charleston Cotton Exchange records, 1880-1952, (6 boxes)
  - Cashbook, 1888-1898 (Box 1)
  - Cashbook, 1916-1931 (Box 1)
  - Assessment of members, 1891-1916 (Box 1)
  - Record, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Reports on cotton movement at Charleston, 1936-1944 (Box 2)
  - Cancelled checks, 1939-1952 (Box 2)
  - Records, 1884-1949 (Box 3)
  - Charleston, South Carolina (Box 3)
  - Marine arrivals, No. 3, 1886-1892 (Box 4)
  - Marine arrivals, No. 4, 1892-1899 (Box 4)
  - Naval stores, No. 2, 1881-1886 (Box 5)
  - Marine arrivals, No. 5, 1899-1905 (Box 5)
  - Cashbook, 1931-1938 (Box 6)
  - Weekly cotton receipts at U.S. ports, 1899-1906 (Box 6)